Good morning, today we do דף מ, Daf Mem, we start with
the משנה Mishnah on the very bottom of ל"ט ע"ב. Lamed Tet
Amud Bet. And we are revisiting in a way issues that came
up
earlier, although before the question was what happens when, meaning we're not
dealing now with the technical act of שחיטה, Shechita, we're dealing more
with sort of the people involved and other types of criteria whereas
in the past the issue was if a non-Jew is a שוחט,
Shochet, here the issue is a Jew is a שוחט Shochet but
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, not עובדי עבודה זרה Ovdei Avodah Zarah or
עובדי כוכבים, Ovei Kochavim, but עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is the concern.
So we dealt with yesterday if a Jew is a שוחט Shochet
and a non-Jew is the owner, is he thinking about עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah and if he is does it matter? Now we're going
to look at the משנה Mishnah about what happens when an actual
Jew is doing it לעבודה זרה, L'Avodah Zarah, under
what conditions does the meat become forbidden? And the thing to remember
which we said yesterday is that when somebody has transgressed the prohibition
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and when the meat is considered to
be an offering to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah are not necessarily always
coincide. So let's take a look at the משנה, Mishnah, very bottom
of ל"ט ע"ב. Lamed Tet Amud Bet.
Anyone have anything on עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in this משנה? Mishnah?
No, some of the ideas definitely, and that's what some of the
תוספות Tosfot seem to be about, but not exactly this משנה. Mishnah.
השוחט לשם הרים לשם גבעות לשם ימים לשם נהרות לשם מדברות, Hashochet
L'Shem Harim, L'Shem Gevaot, L'Shem Yamim, L'Shem Neharot, L'Shem Midbarot,
so somebody is slaughtering this to the mountains and the hills and
the oceans and the rivers and the wildernesses, so presumably as a
form of worshipping these forces of nature or these parts of the
earth. שחיטתו פסולה, Shechitatu Psulah, the שחיטה Shechita is invalid. Okay,
so the גמרא, Gemara, now you might just think that that means
that it's a form of an offering to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
and it's actually fully forbidden in הנאה. Hana'ah. The גמרא Gemara is
going to have an interesting take on that, so let's take a
look, which we'll see that it's not a full offering to עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. But in the משנה Mishnah it just says פסולה,
Psulah, which is like a weak word to use. Okay, let's take
a look now as it continues. שנים אוחזין בסכין, Shnayim Ochazin Besakin,
two people are holding the knife, one of those cases, remember,
one at the head of the knife and the other, one at
one end, one at the other, and they're sort of going back
and forth, we had that before, is it too much of a
sawing action, is there pressure? But here they're doing it in a
way where the technical act is okay. ושוחטין, V'Shochtin, אחד לשם אחד
מכל אלו, Echad L'Shem Echad Mikol Elu,
one has one of these idolatrous intents in his mind, ואחד לשם
דבר כשר, V'Echad L'Shem Davar Kasher,
and the other for a valid thing, meaning presumably just for the
sake of שחיטה Shechita or at least not for the sake of
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. שחיטתו פסולה, Shechitatu Psulah, nevertheless it's invalid because
even one of the participants' thought invalidate. That sort of parallels what
we said yesterday, which is according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer where
the owner's thoughts can invalidate, you don't have to be the whole
owner, you can even be a partial owner and your thoughts can
invalidate. So in parallel here we're saying that rejecting רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, if it is the one who does the שחיטה Shechita whose
thoughts matter, you don't have to be the entire שוחט, Shochet, it's
enough to be
one of the participants and your thoughts have enough power to invalidate.
And I know we brought this up, if you do a מעשה
Ma'aseh then wouldn't it make a difference, like let's say it's my
animal, my knife, and
then you're שוחט shchting with me and I didn't want you to
and you were still thinking לעבודה זרה?
L'Avodah Zarah? So that is very good, that's going to be one
of the first things the גמרא Gemara deals with, so hold off
on that, we will see that today. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says פסולה אין, Psulah In,
yes, if you're thinking about these things it's
invalid, זבחי מתים לא, Zivchei Meitim Lo, but it did not use
the more sort of the stronger phrase that it is an offering
to idols, to the gods, and actually the phrase here is that
it's an offering to the dead, to refer to because you don't
want to refer to, you want to actually
denigrate, thank you, these gods, so you're calling them they're like the
dead, they're made out of wood and stone and whatever, there's no
meaning to them. But anyway, that's what the phrase used and that
means that it's A biblical and B that it's actually forbidden in
benefit. So the משנה Mishnah just says פסולה Psulah which is a
weak term, so why not say that it's a real
offering to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and it's really forbidden in benefit?
So the גמרא Gemara says ורמינהו, U'remihi, I'll ask you on this
where it seems that such a thing would really be considered זבחי
מתים. Zivchei Meitim. We say השוחט לשום הרים לשום גבעות לשום נהרות
לשום מדברות, Hashochet L'Shum Harim, L'Shum Gevaot, L'Shum Neharot, L'Shum Midbarot,
if somebody slaughters an animal for the sake of almost the exact
same list in our משנה, Mishnah, mountains and hills and rivers and
wildernesses, לשום חמה ולבנה, L'Shum Chamah U'Levanah, for the sake of the
sun and the moon, לשום כוכבים ומזלות, L'Shum Kochavim U'Mazalot, the stars
and the
constellations, לשום מיכאל השר הגדול, L'Shum Michael HaSar HaGadol,
for the sake of מיכאל Michael the great angel, לשום שלשול קטנו,
L'Shum Shishuk Katano, even for the sake of a tiny little worm,
so whether you're dealing with the mightiest things of creation or the
lowliest things of creation, and the point here about מיכאל, Michael, I
believe is, that even though obviously מיכאל Michael is a angel that
is accepted within the Jewish belief. So the point about all these
things is these are things that actually exist, whether they exist in
the physical world, they exist in the metaphysical world, they actually exist.
They're just not God, okay? And whether it's the greatest things, mountain,
sun, moon, you know, the greatest angel, or whether it's the tiniest
thing, but these are things that you're worshipping that aren't God. הרי
אלו זבחי מתים, Harei elu zivchei meisim, those are slaughterings to the
dead, meaning that those are idolatrous offerings and therefore forbidden in הנאה.
hana'ah. So exactly including what's in our משנה. mishnah. So because the
גמרא Gemara insists that the word פסולה psulah in our משנה mishnah
is a weak term, it has a problem because here in the
ברייתא braisa it says that these are considered serious offerings to, you
know, עבודה זרה avodah zarah and forbidden in benefit. So how do
you deal with the fact that our משנה mishnah gives it a
much weaker term? So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says, לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult. הא דאמר להר, Ha de'amar le'har, our משנה mishnah
is that you're actually offering it, slaughtering it to the mountain itself,
הא דאמר לגדא דהרא. ha de'amar legada de'hara.
And the other one is you're offering it to the god of
the mountain. Actually גדא gada doesn't mean god, it means the angel
of the mountain, but same point, you're offering it to the spirit
of
the mountain, okay? דייקא נמי, Dayka nami, this can also be inferred
by the language, דקתני דומיא דמיכאל שר הגדול, de'ktani dumya de'Michael sar
ha'gadol, because in this list it also mentions מיכאל Michael the great
angel. So you see we're talking not just about offering it to
physical things, but we're talking to offering it to the spirits that
are that inhabit these or that are over these physical things. שמע
מינה, Sh'ma mina, we hear that. Now why should any of this
matter? Right? If you're offering it, it's an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
who cares if you're worshipping the mountain or the spirit of the
mountain?
So the first point that's relevant here is that the גמרא Gemara
says in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it says if somebody worships a
mountain, they do not make the mountain forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. If
they did, you'd have a really hard time living in this world
because a world that was filled with paganism, right? And even, you
know, what what who were the people that sort of worshipped more
nature, were those Druids or something? Druids? Yeah, what? Right. So anyway,
you know, people are worshipping
actual like holy mountains and this and that all over the place,
these things become forbidden הנאה hana'ah and you can't say, oh, well
they don't own it, but they they do own it, right? Let's
say it is their mountain. So all of a sudden the actual
the earth becomes forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. So the גמרא Gemara learns
that out from the פסוק pasuk which says אלוהיהם על ההרים, eloheihem
al he'harim, if you with
their gods that are on the mountains, ולא ההרים אלוהיהם, ve'lo he'harim
eloheihem, but the mountains themselves are not considered their gods. So therefore
if you actually worship a part of nature itself, which means a
connected to the earth, I shouldn't say of nature, something that is
part connected to the earth, part of the, you know, part of
the earth, then you cannot make it forbidden. If it's מחובר, mechubar,
then your act of bowing down to it does not make it
forbidden. Okay, so תלוש ולבסוף חוברו talush u'levasof chubru we're not talking
about now, right? If I build a house that now is מחובר
mechubar but started detached, that might be different. But something that is
a natural part of the earth and I worship it, I cannot
make it forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara therefore says, ah, so if
I'm worshipping this little worm, okay, that's not connected to the earth.
If I'm worshipping the sun and the moon and the stars, well
I better not be able to make those forbidden, but
but maybe you could also say I don't own those. So it's
a question of exactly how we imagine if the sun and moon
and the stars, they fit into this idea about ההרים. he'harim. Let's
say for now that they do, תוספות Tosafos sort of plays with
that, but let's say they are considered connected. But if I worship
this little worm, that I can make forbidden. But if I worship
the sun and the moon and the mountains, I can't make those
forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara assumes because I can't make them forbidden,
I also the thing that I am offering to them also does
not become forbidden. Now that does not necessarily logically follow, right? Even
though they are part of the earth and is sort of something
that, you know, that's a part of nature and you can't define
nature as a god, but this animal that I'm שוחט-ing shochet could
be an offering to what I believe is a god. So the
גמרא Gemara goes somehow extends that. Now that might be okay if
the you were always consistent with that idea. If we always said
if the object of worship isn't forbidden, the thing offered to it
is not forbidden. However, that's not always the case. First of all,
consider what the גמרא Gemara says. If you actually worship the sun
and the moon and the stars, they or let's even say that
it means the angel מיכאל. Michael. If you מיכאל Michael
or you worship the spirit of the mountain or the spirit of
the sun, moon, and stars, however you categorize sun, moon, and stars.
So the spirit doesn't become forbidden, right? I mean, you know, maybe
they say, well we don't believe in the spirit, but let's say
you worship מיכאל, Michael, would we now say מיכאל Michael you can't
get the benefit from the angel because somebody worshipped? So anyway, in
those cases presumably there's not a thing that becomes forbidden and nevertheless
the offering is forbidden. Now maybe you'll say that's not a great
case because there it's something not physical to begin with so of
course it can't be forbidden. But תוספות Tosafos says, what about or
רש״י Rashi sort of indicate but תוספות Tosafos focuses, what about when
you worship an animal? The גמרא Gemara also says that if you
bow down to an animal, like this has the שלשול. shilshul. שלשול
קטן, shilshul katan, this little worm, you don't make an animal forbidden
through worship. Okay, but nevertheless, an offering to an animal you do
make it forbidden. So the rule is not always consistent. Sometimes the
object of worship does not become forbidden because that somehow is considered
like it's alive, it's part of the earth, and sometimes the thing
that's offered to it is forbidden, and sometimes the thing that's offered
to it is not.
Right, too bad then an animal's not forbidden, depends on my animal
or your animal?
No. No. If it's a living thing, okay, you do not make
it forbidden. I think רש"י Rashi even says this. Let's look at
רש"י. Rashi.
So look at רש"י Rashi דמיא דמיכאל. Dumya deMicha'el. It's about, the
line starts with the word דמיא דמיכאל, Dumya deMicha'el, it's near where
it says עבודה זרה נ"ד ע"א Avoda Zara Nun-Dalet Amud Aleph in
the far right hand margin. So if you see רש"י Rashi or
two lines below that, רש"י Rashi says דלאו מחובר הוא ובעלי חיים
delav mechubar hu uva'alei chayim animals אף על גב דלא מיתסרי משום
עבודת כוכבים af al gav delo mitasri mishum avodat kochavim even though
they're not forbidden as objects of worship, כדאמרינן לקמן דאמוץ מור פירות
אסר רחמנא לגבוה מכלל דלהדיוט שרי, kedamrinan lakaman de'amutz mor peirot asar
rachmana legavo'ah miklal dehedyat shari, מיהו אלוהו מיקרי, mihu eloho mikrei, they're
still considered gods and the thing you worship to it is still
forbidden. So you have this imbalance, right? The mountain is not forbidden
and therefore the thing offered to it is not forbidden. The animal
is not forbidden, the thing offered to it is forbidden. So רש"י
Rashi suggests the following difference. רש"י Rashi says that what do we
mean when we exclude something? When we exclude a mountain, what we're
really saying is הלכה Halacha won't even doesn't even recognize it as
a god. It won't even say—I mean, obviously it doesn't recognize these
things as real gods—but meaning it doesn't even give it a halachic
status as an object of worship. It's not an object of worship
that isn't forbidden. You cannot turn part of the natural world, part
of the earth, into objects of worship. First of all, they're not
even objects, right? They're part of the whole earth. So something that
you don't have control over that is not sort of if you
would chattel and so on, you cannot even define it as an
object of worship. So since the earth, the mountain isn't even an
object of worship, the thing offered to it is not an offering
to an object of worship. רש"י Rashi says animals are different. Animals,
you know, you can own them, you can carry them, they're much
more under your control and definition. So animals are objects of worship,
there's just a technical point that they're not forbidden. But because they
are objects of worship, therefore something offered to them will become forbidden.
Okay, so it's a little bit it gets a little fuzzy, and
that's why you have a big תוספות. Tosafot. I know, and the
תוספות Tosafot says yet another problem, which is what happens when you
worship a mountain? You're חייב chayav for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. You're—so
תוספות Tosafot says how can you tell me the mountain is not
defined as an object of worship if what you just did was
an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara and we're going to execute
you? So that's what this big תוספות Tosafot is trying to figure
this whole thing out. But there are these three different cases and
there's not a good consistency among them. Number one is no matter
what you worship—you worship sun, moon, and stars, mountains, I don't
care—if you're treating it as a god, that's an act of עבודה
זרה avoda zara you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Now when you worship
a mountain, the mountain isn't forbidden and the object you offer to
it is not forbidden. When you worship an animal, the animal is
not forbidden but the object that you offer to it is forbidden.
And you worship the spirit of the mountain?
And when you worship the spirit of the mountain, well the spirit
is not even physical, so we're not even going to talk about
whether it's forbidden, but the object that you offered is forbidden. So
exactly, number one, the first point is whenever you're treating something as
a god, it's an act of עבודה זרה avoda zara you're חייב
מיתה chayav misa in terms of your personal prohibition. Spirit, mountain, whatever.
In terms of what things become forbidden, there are two categories: things
that are part of the earth don't become forbidden and even the
things offered to them do not; things that are animals don't become
forbidden but the thing offered to them is. רש"י Rashi tries to
make the distinction that the earth is not a god but the
thing and therefore the thing offered to it is excluded, although you
still have done עבודה זרה, avoda zara, whereas the animal is a
god, meaning in your mind and is halachically defined as an object
of worship, it's just not forbidden, and but the thing offered to
it does become. So anyway, very complicated. If you want to take
a look, by the way, at how complicated it is, besides the
long תוספות, Tosafot, the very last four words of this long תוספות,
Tosafot, he says ואין להאריך כאן יותר. ve-ein le-ha'arich kan yoter. So
after filling up the entire half of the page, תוספות Tosafot says
but really there's no point in going in greater depth about this
because even this whole discussion just sort of touches the tip of
the iceberg or the tip of the mountain if you will. So
anyway, this is very complicated, the assumption that worshipping the mountain, the
animal does not become forbidden.
To understand the mountain isn't forbidden makes sense, but it's not always
consistent that the thing offered to it is not forbidden just because
based on what the status of the object being worshipped.
Yes, does anybody bring in this שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir La-Azazel in this
discussion? No. Because that is sort of offering to the dead?
Yes, but
the גמרא Gemara does not really want, you know, ever really, at
least that I don't know, maybe in some מדרש Midrash it does,
but it does not ever really like, you know, directly confront the
עבודה זרה avoda zara echoes present in the whole concept of שעיר.
Se'ir. שעיר לעזאזל. Sa'ir L'Azazel. I mean obviously that's very disturbing. So,
but yes. Yeah I understand. The idea of mountains and the spirits
and so on. Yeah.
And you're offering an animal to the mountain spirit.
Right? Right? No, you're right.
Okay, so now let's go, let's keep on going. So after, but,
you know, again, I'm not going to quiz you on exactly all
of those categories because the problem is, it's hard to, as I
said, what I really just wanted to communicate is that there's not
necessarily a good logical reason for exactly all of these divisions. There
are three considerations. Again, number one, are you חייב chayav for עבודה
זרה? Avodah Zarah? That you always are. Number two, is the object
you worship forbidden? There, there are two things that are excluded: parts
of the earth and animals. Number three is, is the thing that
was offered to these things forbidden? And there, there's a strange distinction
between things offered to parts of the earth versus things offered to
animals. Okay, let's continue now in the משנה. Mishnah. So animals are
forbidden, things offered to the earth are not. Right. Okay, so now
let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב הונא:
Amar Rav Huna: הייתה בהמת חברו רבוצה לפני עבודת כוכבים. Hayeta behemot
chavero revutza lifnei avodat kochavim. So your friend's animal, so you don't
own it, and the general principle is you cannot forbid something that
is not yours,
was crouching before an idol. And the presumption about being crouched before
an idol, תוספות Tosafot points out of course, as we've said before
and we will say later, if you slaughter something with thinking about
an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in your mind, you make the object
an offering to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. It doesn't have to be
in the presence of an idol. But here, we're underscoring that it
was in the presence of an idol to make it clear that
this was your intention.
Well, maybe you're trying to save it, like he's trying to שחט
shacht it for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah but he's bringing...
Whatever, no, let's see the whole case. Anyway, but the point is
you don't need it to be in front of an idol if
that was your intention, but having it in front of an idol
makes it clear what your intention was even if you didn't say
anything. Okay, so you are, so, where are we? כיון ששחט בה
סימן אחד אסרה. Keivan sheshachat bah siman echad asrah. As soon as
you שחט shachted one סימן, siman, you don't have to שחט shacht
both סימנים simanim to a full שחיטה, shechitah, you just have to
start cutting into it, you forbid it. Now why is that? סבר
לה כי הא דאמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן. Savar lah ki ha
de'amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan. He holds like what עולא Ulla says
in the name of
רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: אף על פי שאמרו המשתחוה לבהמת חברו לא
אסרה. Af al pi she'amru hamishtachaveh l'vehemat chavero lo asrah. Even though
they say if you bow down and worship your friend's animal, you
do not make it forbidden, עשה בה מעשה אסרה. asah bah ma'aseh
asrah. If you actually do an action to it, you do make
it forbidden. Why? Because the principle first of all is אין אדם
אוסר דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo. So if
you haven't done an action to it, you cannot make it forbidden.
Now somebody's going to say, Michael, I thought you just told me
you can never make animals forbidden for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah if
they're alive. So רש״י Rashi says you can't even make it forbidden
for the מזבח. mizbeach. When you bow down to an animal and
worship it even once it's alive, even though it doesn't become forbidden
for a layperson, it becomes forbidden for the מזבח. mizbeach. But if
you're bowing down to your friend's animal, okay, you cannot make it
forbidden. It's not yours. Who are you to determine the status of
something else that isn't yours? Okay, so your act of bowing down
to it cannot make this into an עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. חוצפה!
chutzpah! You are making my animal into an עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
You have no right, and therefore you cannot make it forbidden. But
comes along, comes along רב הונא Rav Huna and says, עשה בה
מעשה, asah bah ma'aseh, or I'm sorry, first עולא Ulla in the
name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, עשה בה מעשה אסרה. asah
bah ma'aseh asrah. If you do an action to it, then the
fact that you are physically doing something to it and changing it,
then you actually are showing you, then you actually can define its
status because you're actually are physically controlling it. Now an obvious way
to point this out, by the way, sometimes that's because the whole
status is a result of its physical nature. Like I wouldn't say
that if I took your meat out of your refrigerator and took
your milk out of your refrigerator and cooked them
together, אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam oser davar she'eino
shelo. Right? Because who cares about that it's mine or yours or
whatever, there's a physical reality of this being meat and milk cooked
together. Okay, so there, clearly that's true. But here, an animal with
a cut neck is not forbidden. It's not the physical reality per
se that makes it forbidden. It is still my designation of it
as an object of worship. So you could still say, I'm not
entitled to designate your animal as an object of worship. But if
I am physically taking control over it and changing it and cutting
into it, then that actually, my designation of it is meaningful and
it does become an object of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So the
first principle is if I worship your object, I don't make it
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah because it's yours, not mine, I can't redefine
its הלכתי halachic status. But if I physically change it and physically
take control then I can redefine its status and turn it into
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. That's the statement of עולא Ulla in the
name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רב הונא Rav Huna is coming
in and saying you don't even have to do a full שחיטה.
shechitah. The basic point is is that you're physically changing it. So
as soon as you begin to cut it, there it's considered to
be an act of change and therefore it's an offering to עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah and therefore it is forbidden.
Even if you like stabbed it, it doesn't make a difference.
Now, you could ask what would happen if within the worship of
this god, this would not be considered a legitimate form of offering?
That might be, because within the... Presumably although I would have to
double check actually, but basically, yeah because there's all these discussions in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin about this, about sort of קורבנות פנימיים korbanos pnimiyim and
משמש בעבודת פנים. meshamesh ba'avodas pnim. If I
just stabbed it in this form of worship and I stabbed it
then it may not, right. So
to what degree does that determine what also what's considered to be
a form of offering is a good question and I have to
review that. But anyway, his point is, is that, is that you
don't have to do a full שחיטה, shechita, you just have to
do an action to and then your offering of it to עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara is meaningful even though it's not yours. Okay, so
that is the statement. So now let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רב נחמן לרב הונא. Amar Rav Nachman leRav Huna. So רב
נחמן Rav Nachman asks רב הונא. Rav Huna. השוחט חטאת בשבת בחוץ.
Hashocheit chatas beShabbos bachutz. So you are שחיטה shechting an animal that's
a חטאת, chatas, a sin offering, and it's שבת, Shabbos, and you're
שחיטה shechting it out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So already
you've got two problems, right? You're שחיטה shechting an animal on שבת,
Shabbos, so you're מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos by... by the way, you're
מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos not only by שחיטה shechting an animal, even
by just, you know, even just by making a wound, doing something
that draws blood is considered חבורה, chabura, is considered a מלאכה melacha
on שבת. Shabbos. The only question is that it has to be
מתקן, metakein, it has to affect some positive change, not just be
damaging, right? So if you beat somebody up on שבת Shabbos then
and you cause a and you cause blood to flow, you're not
חייב. chayav. If however you draw blood because you want to use
it for, you know, you know, for a blood bank or something,
then you are חייב. chayav. So the so drawing blood is a
מלאכה melacha if it's for a positive function. What positive function is
it here? Well if you שחיטה shecht it you can eat it,
but there's a little problem because we're gonna see it's a חטאת,
chatas, whatever, there's all these reasons you're not going to be able
to eat it. But nevertheless, as far as the בן נח Ben
Noach is concerned, at least it's no longer אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. Okay, so the fact that that is considered enough of
a fix of something positive of this שחיטה shechting of it that
it stops it from being אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. So
you שחט shechted it on שבת, Shabbos, that's a מלאכה, melacha, it's
a חטאת chatas and you're שחיטה shechting it out of the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that's an act that's חייב כרת, chayav kares, קדשים
בחוץ, kodashim bachutz, and as if that weren't enough, לעבודת כוכבים. la'avodas
kochavim. While you're doing this, you're also working doing it as an
offering to a god, to an עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. You're doing
three things each one of which is either חייב מיתה chayav misa
or חייב כרת. chayav kares. And but you happen to be doing
them all
בשוגג, beshogeg, of course. So therefore the גמרא Gemara sometimes likes figuring
out how you can do one action and how many קרבנות korbanos
can you get out of one action? So if you did it
all בשוגג, beshogeg, חייב שלוש חטאות. chayav shalosh chata'os. You have to
bring three sin offerings. Because if it says מזיד meizid you can't
kill somebody three times, it's not as interesting. But if it does
it בשוגג beshogeg you can say you're חייב chayav for all three
different things. Okay. שוגג Shogeg is by accident.
By accident. But how can you do these things by accident?
So let's say you did not know that they were forbidden. Either
by שבת Shabbos you could say I didn't realize it was שבת.
Shabbos. By the חטאת chatas you could say I didn't realize it
was a חטאת. chatas. But עבודה זרה Avoda Zara you would have
to say, oh, I didn't realize it was forbidden to worship עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. Okay, so there is a possibility of like, oh,
I didn't realize that this thing was an idol, but if that
were true, then it's not שוגג, shogeg, then it's not an offering
to עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, right? Then you just thought that you
were in front of a statue, not in front of an idol,
you weren't intending it to be an offering to a, to a
false god, so it's not שוגג shogeg then it's not עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara at all. So by a שוגג shogeg עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara much more has to be that you didn't realize that this
was forbidden even you might realize in principle it's forbidden to worship
עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, maybe I didn't realize that this was included
in that category or something of that nature. Okay. Still a stretch.
Okay. ואי אמרת, V'ei amart, that's the case. ואי אמרת כיון ששחט
בה סימן אחד אסרה, v'ei amart keivan sheshachat bah siman echad asrah,
if you're going to tell me that as soon as you begin
to cut into the animal you've made it an offering of עבודה
זרה, Avoda Zara, right? Because that's part of the point. Part of
the point was not just when can you redefine your friend's object,
but also at what stage of שחיטה shechting something to עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara is it considered to be an offering already and its
status becomes forbidden. So if you tell me something is considered an
offering from the very beginning of the שחיטה, shechita, okay, אשחוטי חוץ
לא ליחייב, ashchutei chutz lo lichayiv, why are you חייב chayav for
שחיטה shechting something out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? דכתשי בעפר
הוא. dechtishi b'afra hu. You're cutting into dirt. What does that mean?
You're only חייב chayav for offering something out of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash when you do a full שחיטה, shechita, not just when
you begin the שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so when I begin the שחיטה,
shechita, by when I cut the first
סימן, siman, I've made this an offering to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
I've made this therefore, you know, forbidden in benefit, an offering to
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and so on. Now when I finish the
שחיטה, shechita, I'm not חייב chayav for שחיטה shechting a קרבן korban
out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if in this last סימן
siman it's no longer a קרבן. korban. You know, it's an offering
to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. It doesn't become both an offering to
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and a קרבן. korban. As soon as it's
an offering to עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, it stops being a קרבן,
korban, okay? And therefore, I'm not I haven't finished the שחיטה shechita
of a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. By the
time I'm finished, it's no longer a קרבן. korban. Now רש"י Rashi
says why don't you also say you're not no longer doing a
good שחיטה shechita on שבת? Shabbos? This is for the reason I
said, that for שבת Shabbos you don't have to do a שחיטה,
shechita, you just have to wound in a way that derives some
benefit. So the end of the day is is that for non-Jews
it's no longer אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. The fact that
it's an offering to עבודה זרה Avoda Zara represents we non-Jews are
not forbidden to eat offerings to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. They're forbidden
to worship עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, not presumably not forbidden to eat
offerings to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
They're not forbidden from having my חטאת? chatas?
Presumably apparently not. Okay, so anyway, and another interesting question would be,
even if let's say in theory they were, is it enough that
you've also at least removed one problem from it?
But even if they don't plan on giving it to any בן
נח, Ben Noach, correct.
There is some benefit that you that this has achieved. This has
achieved some constructive purpose in this world. Okay, so anyway, but the
גמרא's Gemara's question is, at least why are you חייב chayav for
finishing the שחיטה shechita of a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash? By the time you're doing the second סימן, siman, it's
no longer a קרבן. korban. Okay, if you say that you define
it as an offering of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara as soon as
you begin the process. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers.
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, הכא בחטאת העוף עסקינן. hacha b'chatas
ha'of askinan. Remember he said that's said a חטאת. chatas. So we're
talking about a specific חטאת, chatas, a bird חטאת. chatas. Remember, what's
a bird חטאת? chatas? You only have to cut one סימן. siman.
דכולהו בהדי הדדי קא אתו. D'kulu behadi hadadi ka asu. They're all
coming with that one סימן. siman. That one סימן siman is the
the act of making it an offering to עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara,
the act of making it a שחיטה shechita of a חטאת chatas
outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and of stopping it from being
אבר מן החי eiver min hachai for non-Jews. Okay, so they all
come with the cutting of the one סימן. siman. That's a nice
little answer, but the גמרא's Gemara's not happy. מכדי, Michdi, says the
גמרא, Gemara, let's see. רב הונא כמאן אמרה לשמעתיה? Rav Huna k'man
amrah l'shmateih? Who is רב הונא Rav Huna going by? כדאולה, K'de'Ula,
like עולא. Ula. עולא Ula says, ועולא מעשה כל דהו קאמר. V'Ula
ma'aseh kol dahu ka'amar. עולא Ula says as soon as you do
any action, you make it forbidden. אסרה במעשה. Asrah b'ma'aseh. Now, you
don't really have to interpret that by עולא. Ula. עולא Ula could
mean that you do the full act, you שחט shecht it. But
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, as soon as רב הונא
Rav Huna says you don't have to do the full act, and
you only have to cut one סימן, siman, there is no significance
of one סימן siman over a half of a סימן siman or
over a quarter of a סימן. siman. Once we're interpreting עולא Ula
to mean you don't have to do the full act of שחיטה
shechita to make somebody's animal forbidden when you offer it, then then
it means even any part of it. As long as you begin
to physically change it, you make it forbidden. There's no difference between
one סימן siman and a half of a סימן. siman. So the
גמרא Gemara says the problem still exists. As soon as you begin
cutting, it's עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Only when you finished the סימן
siman is it considered to be an offering or a קרבן, korban,
and at that stage it's no longer a קרבן. korban. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says once you don't need two סימנים, simanim, even
a little of a סימן siman is a problem and your answer
you still have this problem.
So basically the question is, why why do you say one סימן?
siman? Meaning it has to be both.
No, but we are assuming that when רב הונא, Rav Huna, no,
עולא Ula could have meant two סימנים. simanim. But once רב הונא
Rav Huna says that you don't need to cut two סימנים, simanim,
it's enough to cut one סימן, siman, then there's no logical difference
between one סימן siman and a quarter of a סימן. siman. Right,
that's what I'm saying, meaning why why No, but the question is
why didn't רב הונא Rav Huna say this? We assume that when
רב הונא Rav Huna said one סימן, siman, he didn't mean literally
one סימן. siman. Because we don't we can't accept that there's any
significance to one סימן. siman. So we assume that what רב הונא
Rav Huna meant is as soon as you begin cutting. Once that's
true, we're back to our question. You begin cutting, it's an offering
to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. How are you חייב chayav for שחטינג
shechting it out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? By the time
you're done שחטינג, shechting, even if it's only one סימן, siman, it's
no longer a קרבן, korban, it's already an offering to עבודה זרה.
Avoda Zara. Okay, so let's see what the
גמרא Gemara is. אלא אמר מר זוטרא משמיה דרב פפא, Ella amar
Mar Zutra mishmeih d'Rav Papa, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what
are
we
talking about? כגון שהיה חצי קנה פגום והוסיף עליו כל שהוא וגמרו.
k'gon she'hayah chatzi kaneh pagum v'hosif alav kol shehu v'gemaro.
So remember we had this case before. You had your trachea was
half cut. Trachea could be half cut without it being a טריפה.
treifa. And you went and you needed the tiniest amount of a
cut, you added to that half cut, and therefore you made the
trachea the majority cut. Now it's a חטאת, chatas, now we know
why it has to be a חטאת. chatas. It's a bird חטאת
chatas where one סימן siman suffices. So you did the tiniest little
act, but because it's a bird חטאת, chatas, that made it a
good שחיטה shechita for the bird, which meant that
it was
No, for שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz it's שחיטת חוץ, shchitas chutz, not
מליקת חוץ, melikas chutz, we know that, the פסוקים psukim tell us
that. Okay, so now we understand why it said חטאת. chatas. Yes,
it's true, for עבודה זרה avoda zara the tiniest little act makes
it forbidden. So how will we get a case where the tiniest
little act and the שחיטה shchita will come at the exact same
time? In this scenario where it's a bird חטאת, chatas, so you
only need one סימן, siman, it's already half cut, and in that
scenario you'll get the tiny little tiniest little act that's meaningful for
עבודה זרה avoda zara and the שחיטה, shchita, because you now made
it from fifty percent to fifty-one percent, all coming at the exact
same time. So that's why we said חטאת chatas in order to
create exactly this way in which a tiny little act and the
שחיטה shchita come at the same time.
So because of a statement of an אמורא, amora, we're completely kind
of re-reading...
Oh, and the גמרא gemara never
does that in the past.
Oh.
All right, anyway, well
that's his opinion, other people disagree. Okay, so דכולי בי די הדי
קשיא. d'chulei bei di hadchi kashei. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa,
so רב פפא Rav Papa says, and here's sort of like what
Michael was saying, wow, that was a big change. אי לאו דאמר
רב הונא סימן אחד לא הוי חטאת תיובתיה. ilav d'amar Rav Huna
siman echad, lo havei chatas tyuvtei. If רב הונא Rav Huna had
not said that just cutting one סימן siman is enough to make
it an offering to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, this case about shechting
this חטאת chatas outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would not have
been a problem. It's your cow, but גמרא Gemara says no, because
since it's a חטאת, chatas, you don't get to benefit from it.
Who's going to eat the חטאת? chatas? The כהנים, kohanim, okay? So
קדשי, kodshei, certainly קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim are not really considered yours
anymore. So he's saying it's like this, I could have gotten out
of that חטאת chatas problem the following way. Remember, the whole חטאת
chatas problem is you began it, you already made it עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, you're not yet, you're not חייב chayav at the end
when you finish שחיטה. shechting. Okay, but first of all, that's all
because רב הונא Rav Huna got us into that corner. Number one,
רב הונא Rav Huna said you got a problem as soon as
you begin. If he would have said the whole problem is at
the end, we wouldn't have even started with the question. Even if
רב הונא Rav Huna is going to tell us it's, you got
a problem when you begin, I could have said that's by your
own cow, not by your friend's, and this חטאת chatas is not
your own. Once it's a חטאת, chatas, it's basically קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim, it belongs to God, it's not yours, so maybe there the
beginning of the process can't define the status, maybe you can never
define the status, or maybe you can only define the status when
you finish the שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, so רב הונא Rav Huna created
the problem because he said two חידושים. chiddushim. Number one, beginning of
the שחיטה shechitah is enough to make it עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
and number two is that even enough to make your friend's cow
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And that got us into having to redefine
this whole case because if you already made it עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, why are you חייב chayav by the time you get to
the end? Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. פשיטא.
Peshita. The גמרא Gemara says it's obvious. I don't know how obvious
it was. That was very helpful actually in clarifying רב הונא's Rav
Huna position, but anyway no. מהו דתימא, Mahu deteyma, I might have
thought, כיון דקני ליה לכפרה, keivan dekani lei lechapara, since you own
the חטאת chatas for atonement, meaning it's true, it's not yours, but
even though it's not yours in the sense of like technical ownership
anymore, but the reality is is that you are, you get atonement
for it, it's still called your חטאת, chatas, it's still called ראובן
Reuven's חטאת, chatas, right? Even though technically you might not own it
in terms of, you know, normal monetary purpose. So since it's still
yours that it atones for you, כדי דמיא, kidei damya, it's enough
yours that your act of עבודה זרה avodah zarah you can define
its status. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan not, and that raises interesting
questions. When we say you can't define something, make something forbidden that
isn't yours, how do you define what it means to be yours
or not yours? Does it go by normal דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot,
or does it go like if this is enough mine that I'm
going to bring it as a קרבן, korban, then I have enough
of a control and relationship over it that I might be able
to actually define its status for this issue
of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says I
might have thought that, he's telling me not that way. We're actually
going to see in a minute that there are those that actually
hold that. That yes, by a חטאת chatas it is enough yours
and it will become an object of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay,
so what have we said? We've said you cannot make your friend's
thing forbidden until you do an action. Your thing without an action,
your friend's until you do an action, that we know. Comes along
רב הונא Rav Huna and makes two חידושים. chiddushim. Number one is
you make something an offering to עבודה זרה avodah zarah as soon
as you begin the action, and number two is even when it's
your friend's, and I might have thought there you need a much
bigger action, no, even the beginning of the action is also sufficient.
And a חטאת, chatas, says the גמרא, Gemara, would have been like
your friend's, and therefore you wouldn't have been, you know, you need
to follow those rules. But because of רב הונא's Rav Huna ruling,
we've got this problem that you made it forbidden at the very
beginning of the process, and therefore how are you חייב chayav for
שחיטה shechting it at the end of the process? Now we're going
to see an opposing opinion. Let's take a look. רב נחמן רב
עמרם ורב יצחק אמרי, Rav Nachman Rav Amram veRav Yitzchak amri, so
now we have three אמוראים Amoraim that say אין אדם אוסר דבר
שאינו שלו. ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo. They agree with עולא
Ulla's teaching. They disagree with עולא Ulla's teaching. They say even if
you שחט shecht your friend's cow, if it's not your cow, you
cannot make it forbidden. So even if you do an action, they
not only disagree with רב הונא, Rav Huna, they actually disagree with
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan אמר עולא אמר רב יוחנן, amar Ulla amar
Rav Yochanan, that even if you do a full action, even if
you שחט shecht your friend's cow completely, you cannot make it forbidden
to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. If it's not yours, you cannot redefine
its status. Okay, and you can eat it. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says מיתיבי, masvei, I'll ask you on this, השוחט חטאת בשבת
בחוץ לעבודת כוכבים חייב שלש חטאות.
hashuchet chatas beshabbos bechutz
la'avodas kochavim chayav shalosh chatas. So again this case you're חייב. chayav.
Now what's the problem? It's beautiful. Since you said that you don't
make it forbidden, there's no question to ask. But the גמרא Gemara
says oh, but ואוקימנא בחטאת העוף בחצי קנה פגום. ve'ukimna bechatas ha'of
bechatzi kanei pagum. But we just got through saying that the reason
it mentioned a חטאת, chatas, the גמרא Gemara is so enamored with
this brilliant answer, why did it say חטאת? chatas? Why didn't it
just say any קרבן? korban? Oh, because a חטאת chatas allows you
to do a tiny little act and in that tiny act both
do a שחיטה shechitah and a tiny act is enough for עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. So we've now explained that that's why it mentioned
חטאת, chatas, in order to allow this tiny act to be a
שחיטה. shechitah. So טעמא דחטאת העוף דכולה בהדי הדדי אתיין, taima dechatas
ha'of dechula bahadi hadada asyan, so we've just explained brilliantly how because
it's a חטאת העוף, chatas ha'of, that allows all these to come
at the same time. Which would indicate that if it weren't this
special case, they wouldn't come at the same time and you would
make it forbidden beforehand. אבל זבח לא, aval zevach lo, a normal
sacrifice like a שלמים, shelamim, it wouldn't be true. So according to
you, why do you need this special case? Case of a חטאת
העוף chatas ha'of and a tiny little act and then they all
come at the same time? According to you, even a normal קרבן,
korban, what's true about a normal קרבן? korban? It's not yours, we
just got through saying, once it's קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim you don't
it's not yours at all. So if it's not yours, your act
of שחיטה shechitah doesn't make it forbidden, and you don't need any
special cases. So why mention a חטאת, chatas, just say any קרבן.
korban. You're שוחט-ing shochet it for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you're not
making it forbidden cause it's not yours. And therefore all these obligations,
all these transgressions come at the same time when you finish the
שחיטה. shechitah.
ואי אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, ve-i ein adam oser davar
she-eino shelo, if you can't make something forbidden that's not yours, מאי
איריא חטאת העוף, mai irya chatas ha'of, why mention a bird חטאת?
chatas? אפילו חטאת
בהמה נמי, afilu chatas behemah nami, even a bird even an animal
חטאת, chatas, even an animal עולה. olah. So כי קאני ליה לכפרה
כדידיה דמיא, ki ka-nei lei le-khaparah ke-didei damya, the גמרא Gemara says
here the thing that it rejected a minute ago. Since it's your
קרבן korban that is enough yours to make it forbidden for עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. So this idea that you can't make something forbidden
that isn't yours, now we're saying but a קרבן korban even though
דיני ממונות dinei mamonot monetarily is not yours anymore, but since you
it's defined as yours and it works for you, you have enough
of a relationship to it that your act of worshipping it or
your act of offering it to עבודה זרה avodah zarah can redefine
it. Even with even the little פחות משחיטה? pachot mi-shechitah? Yeah, the
same way you can redefine your own animal, even by bowing down
to it. You don't have to finish שוחט-ing... shochet Oh no no
no, it's still the חטאת העוף chatas ha'of case. Yeah, presumably that
they agree to. So what have we said now? We have said
that רב הונא Rav Huna says two חיובין. chiyuvim. Number one, at
what stage when you שוחט shochet something לעבודה זרה la-avodah zarah do
you make it forbidden? So says רב הונא Rav Huna or the
way the גמרא Gemara interprets רב הונא, Rav Huna, even the slightest
cut, even just beginning the שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, that's number one. That
has not been explicitly debated, although the גמרא Gemara points out in
theory you could disagree with that and say you have to do
the full שחיטה. shechitah. But then we have a more serious debate
which the גמרא Gemara acknowledges, which is: can I make somebody else's
cow forbidden if I do an action to it? An action of
worshipping it to as עבודה זרה avodah zarah or bringing it as
a offering to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. רב הונא Rav Huna says
yes, and רב הונא Rav Huna says even a tiny action will
make it considered forbidden and defines your control over it. And now
we have these three אמוראים, Amoraim, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, רב עמרם,
Rav Amram, רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, that say even a big action,
if it's your friend's animal, even if you completely שוחט-ed shochet it,
you cannot redefine your friend's animal as an offering, as עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. You're חייב מיתה chayav misah for your worshipping עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, but you can never redefine your friend's animal. אין אדם
אוסר דבר שאינו שלו ein adam oser davar she-eino shelo is categorical.
There's the possibility the גמרא Gemara acknowledges of a middle case, which
is maybe not a tiny action,
but maybe not never, but maybe only a
big action. Okay, but now we're going to two extremes. רב הונא
Rav Huna says a tiny action, these אמוראים Amoraim say you can
never make your friend's thing forbidden even with a big action. But
they both agree that in the case of קדשים kodashim even the
slightest act even the slightest thing would make it forbidden for different
reasons. רב הונא Rav Huna says for קדשים kodashim you can make
it forbidden because you can make somebody else's thing forbidden. So he
considers קדשים kodashim to be somebody else's, but he's of his position
that you can make somebody else's forbidden. And these אמוראים Amoraim say
by this case of קרבן korban you can make it forbidden because
they consider קרבן korban to be enough yours
and not your friend, not God, it's enough yours. You have enough
a relationship to it that therefore you can make it forbidden. And
even its tiniest
action? Yes. So presumably they both agree by קדשים kodashim but for
different reasons. רב הונא Rav Huna says cause it's somebody else's but
I don't care, and they say cause I consider the קרבן korban
to
be yours and therefore they both agree that once it's, you know,
that for whatever reason, then you can make it forbidden and they
do agree that even a small action. Okay so we will continue
with this.